Guide to the Capitol Hill Restoration Society records, 1904-2012 MS2009
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Capitol Hill Restoration Society records
1904-2012
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Capitol Hill Restoration Society
MS2009
97 Linear Feet Boxes 1-194
Collection consists of material gathered and created by the Capitol Hill Restoration Society as a function of their work as an advocacy agency in the Capitol Hill neighborhood. The type of material in the collection includes newsletters, correspondence, photographs, treasurer reports, maps, reports, and studies. This material dates from 1904-2012 with the majority of the material falling within the dates 1958-2012. Topics of interest include Eastern Market, Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, Yost House, House Tours, and Traffic.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The Capitol Hill Restoration Society donated the bulk of these records in 2000 with continuing donations made periodically.
The Capitol Hill Restoration Society donated boxes 168-194, or accession 2014.015, on May 8, 2014.
Historical Note
The Capitol Hill Restoration Society (CHRS) formed in 1955 as an advocacy group with the goal of preserving the character and architecture of the Capitol Hill neighborhood. Prior to 1955 citizens' associations had existed including the Capitol Hill Southeast Citizens' Association and the Southeast Civic Association. The CHRS, however, filled a specific role as a public forum for residents to promote and protect the predominately residential character of the community. One of the most significant achievements towards this goal was the successful placement of the Capitol Hill neighborhood on the National Register of Historic Places in 1976. Thereafter residents were required to obtain permission to make changes to the exterior of their houses. This ensures that the physical look of the houses reflect the historical integrity of the time period in which they were built.
Prior to 1791 when Pierre Charles L'Enfant was hired to design the city of Washington D.C., the land now known as Capitol Hill was farmland. Many of the neighborhood's first residents were the construction workers hired to build the Capitol. In 1799 the building of the Navy Yard brought in additional jobs and residents. Following the Civil War, the population of the Capitol Hill neighborhood increased steadily as the Federal Government grew and the Navy Yard became the world's largest ordnance producer and engineering research center. The growth of the Federal Government and its need for building space led to the demolition of many of the original buildings in the Capitol Hill neighborhood. Fortunately, many of the late 19th and early 20th Century buildings, especially the homes, remain. The Capitol Hill Restoration Society (CHRS) story begins with the restoration movement that followed World War II. The CHRS mission is a good summary of the type of work done by the organization. The mission includes protecting Capitol Hill's residential character by challenging threatening and inappropriate development and incursions into the neighborhood by increased cross-town traffic, helping residents to protect their property values, and offers advice on the maintenance and repair of historic buildings, ensuring that city-wide zoning regulations are applied consistently, in a manner that enhances the neighborhood, working to improve city services such as tree and park maintenance, street repairs, trash collection, and recycling and engages in community issues like public safety, surplus school disposal, and organizing activities like the annual House and Garden Tour that promote Capitol Hill as a fine residential community.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of material gathered and created by the Capitol Hill Restoration Society as a function of their work as an advocacy agency in the Capitol Hill neighborhood. The type of material in the collection includes newsletters, correspondence, photographs, treasurer reports, maps, reports, and studies. This material dates from 1904-2012 with the majority of the material falling within the dates 1958-2012. Topics of interest include Eastern Market, Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, Yost House, House Tours, and Traffic.
Collection Organization
Organized into 19 series: Ad hoc committees and task forces, Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, Directories, Eastern Market, Peter Glickert papers, Graphics, Historic district committee, Historical files, Leukhardt family papers, Gregory New papers, Presidents' papers, Arline Roback papers, Standing committees, Treasurer's office records, Yost house committee, oversize materials, minutes, Accession #2009.061, and Accession 2004.001.
Maps; Barney Circle (Washington, D.C.); Photographs; Citizens' associations; Urban renewal; Zoning; Historic preservation; Eastern Market (Washington, D.C.); Capitol Hill (Washington, D.C.); Urban transportation; Express highways
- Ad hoc committees and task forces, 1955-1989; MS2009 Series 1; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains legislative bills, reports, awards, and questionnaires. These materials cover the dates 1955-89. The CHRS has many temporary committees and task forces that are formed to respond to a particular project or issue. This series relays the work of several of these task forces Examples include the Barney Circle Steering Committee, the Prison Task Force, and the Traffic Management Task Force.
  - Barney Circle Steering Committee, (1), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barney Circle Steering Committee, (2), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boundaries Committee Report, and Recommendations, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Capitol Hill Community Council: Eigth Annual Caper - Documents, tickets, and bills, 1968 September 22; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 6)
  - Capitol Hill Prospectus, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congressional Cemetery, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First District Substation, Preservation Task Force, (1), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - First District Substation, Preservation Task Force, (2), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - First District Substation, Preservation Task Force, (3), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Historic District Application for Capitol Hill Historic District, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Historic District Background, Clippings, and Articles, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Historic District Capitol Hill Social History by Michael S. Franch, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Historic District Capitol Hill Senate and House Bill, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Historic District D.C. Law 2-144 Historic Landmark and Historic District Protection Act, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Historic District Joint Committee on Landmark Historic District, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Historic District Marginal Buildings and Plans for Consolidation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Historic District Testimony before Joint Committee regarding District boundaries December 9, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Historic Preservation Advisory Council on HP/Procedures for the Protection and Historic Cultural Properties, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Historic Preservation Washington Navy Yard Building 111, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kennedy Center Plans, 1964 - 1965; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 3)
  - Mattingly Family Fund (fire at 906 Independence Ave), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Planning Commission - "Goals for Living", 1963 October - December; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 1)
  - National Capital Planning Commission, Circa 1960s; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 2)
  - Old Market Gallery Art Show - Receipts, Invoices, Plans, and Publicity, 1961 June; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 5)
  - Prison Task Force Articles and Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Prison Task Force Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Prison Task Force Gallinger Municipal Hospital Landmark Application, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Prison Task Force Report of the Historic Preservation Review Board, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Prison Task Force Testimony, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Property Tax Reassessment, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Providence Hospital, (1), 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Providence Hospital, (2), 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Providence Hospital (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Providence Hospital (4), 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Providence Hospital, (5), 1955-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Public Hearing Notices, 1960 - 1961; Series 1 (Box 164, Folder 4)
  - Public Schools (1), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Public Schools (2), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Restoration Award, Plaque for Frederick Douglas House, 316 A St., NE, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Restoration Award, Plaque for John Philip Sousa House, 636 G St., SE, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Restoration Award, Plaque for Yost House (1), 1980 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Restoration Award, Plaque for Yost House (2), 1980 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Traffic Management Task Force 4th and 6th Streets (2 way conversion), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Bicycle Plan, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Bus Garage, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Independence Ave. and 12th Street Traffic Light, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Lincoln Park, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Meeting Documentation, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Meeting Documentation, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Meeting Documentation, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Meeting Documentation, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Meeting Documentation, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Parking Study phase I, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Pennsylvania Ave., 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Pennsylvania Ave. Bridge Restoration, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Questionnaire, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Traffic Task Force Third Street Ramp, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Truck Restrictions, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Traffic Management Task Force Waterfront Planning Study for Anacostia, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, 1981-1997; MS2009 Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet
  This series contains articles, correspondence, reports, and environmental impact statements. This material dates from 1981-97. The series has two subject divisions including background material and freeway modification reports. The series includes many of the reports written by the DC Department of Transportation and other groups such as the National Capital Planning Commission. The Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project was a proposed link between Interstate 395 and Interstate 295. The goal was to provide drivers, specifically targeting commuters, with a way to cross the city without using local streets. The project encountered a lot of neighborhood opposition and construction never began.
  - Background, articles, and letters: Barney Circle, 1988-1996 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Background, articles, and letters: 3rd Street Ramp, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Background, articles, and letters: Barney Circle Background, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Background, articles, and letters: Barney Circle Background, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Background, articles, and letters: Barney Circle Background, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Background, articles, and letters: Barney Circle Design and Traffic, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study (I-295) Final Environmental Impact Statement Vol.1 of 2, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study (I-295) Final Environmental Impact Statement Vol. 2 of 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study (I-295) Draft Environmental Impact Statement February, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study DC DOT Agreement DT 8104 Final First Interim Report, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modifications, Preservation, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Freeway modification: Preservation Trust Exhibit, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Freeway modification: The Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, 1984-1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, 1983-1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, 1984-1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Design June, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Design, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study DC DOT Job Number DT 8140 First Interim Report December 7, 1981 December 07 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study DC DOT Job Number DT 8140 First Interim Report Appendices, 1981 December 07 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study DC DOT Job Number DT 8140 First Interim Report Plans and Profiles, 1981 December 07 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Study -- Design Public Hearing Report Design Public Hearing, 1988 May 11-12 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project Environmental Assessment, 1995 August (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project Design Study Report, 1989 December (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Freeway modification: National Park Service, Barney Circle Freeway Modification Project, Capitol Hill Transportation Task Force, Hill Rag, National Capital Planning Commission, Committee of 100 on the Federal City, Washington Post, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Freeway modification: Barney Circle - Citizen's Advisory Group - U.S. Department of Interior, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Directories, 1968-1992; MS2009 Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series includes both completed directories and those within various stages of production. The material covers the dates 1968-92.
  - Directory, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Directory, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Directory, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Directory, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Directory, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Directory, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Directory, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Directory, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Directory, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Directory, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Directory, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Directory, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Directory, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Directory, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Directory, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Directory, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer records: 1981 Bills (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer records: 1981 Expenses (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Treasurer records: Forms, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer records: Miscellaneous, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer records: Receipts, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer Records, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer Records, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards A-C, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards C-I, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards J-P, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards P-Z, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer records: Index to Services, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer records: Index to Services, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer Records, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer Records, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer Records, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer records: Index Cards, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Eastern Market, 1971-1991; MS2009 Series 4; 3.5 Linear feet
  This series contains meeting materials, correspondence, resolutions, studies, articles of incorporation, newsletters, technical reports, engineering reports, survey, by-laws, and testimony. These materials date from 1971-91. The series contains material related to the Community Development Corporation, Development Study and Technical Report, Eastern Market Planning Committee, Eastern Market Preservation and Development Corporation (EMPDC). Much of the material within the series deals with renovation issues, has material that deals with the District government, and gives a good sense of the city's work regarding the Market. The material related to the EMPDC is a good set of records for that organization from 1988-91 and includes documents such as correspondence, meeting minutes, and budget.
  Eastern Market located at 7th St. and North Carolina Avenue is the only publicly-owned fresh-food market in Washington D.C. The Market's South Hall was built in 1873 and the North Hall followed in 1907. The Market is listed on the National Register of Historic Places. In 1987, the Eastern Market Preservation Development Corporation formed to implement a restoration plan created by the Eastern Market Neighborhood Commission organized by the DC government. Unfortunately, the DC Historic Preservation Office deemed the plan inappropriate and very little preservation work has been completed. Currently the city and the Eastern Market management groups are engaged in litigation to determine who controls the property.
  - Community Development Corporation: CDC Meetings, 1974-1988 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Community Development Corporation: Agreements of Lease, Supplements 1-4; Renovation, Phase IV (March); Farmers' Line (August); Alcoholic Beverages (Nov); Lease Agreement, Crummel School, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Community Development Corporation: June - EMC letter to Council members re: Community Development Resolution; ANC6B; Mayor's EM study announcement, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Community Development Corporation: March -- Scope of Services for Eastern Market Area and Streetscape Study, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Community Development Corporation: April - May -- Eastern Market Area and Streetscape Study, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Community Development Corporation: June, July -- Community Steering Committee for the Eastern Market Area Study, Organization Chart, Recommendations, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    General note
    Selected items from this folder are described below. Please note that this is not a comprehensive list of the materials within this folder.
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Steven L. Cymrot, 1982 June 15; Item 1
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Walter Dodd, 1982 June 11; Item 2
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Paul Hays, 1982 July 19; Item 3
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Chuck Brome, 1982 June 05; Item 4
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and James Mayo, 1982 June 10; Item 5
    - Correspondence: Marion Barry and J. Andrew Scallan, 1982 July 08; Item 6
    - Correspondence: Pennsylvania Avenue Business Association, 1982 July 20; Item 7
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Cindy Donaldson, 1982 July 09; Item 8
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Sharon Nelson (Abramson), 1982 July 01; Item 9
    - Correspondence: Marion Barry and Peter Eveleth, 1982 July 21; Item 10
    - Correspondence: Marion Barry and Richard H. Chused, undated; Item 11
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Gottlieb C. Simon, 1982 July 06; Item 12
    - Correspondence: Peter Eveleth and Joseph Isom, 1982 July 16; Item 13
  - Community Development Corporation: March -- Eastern Market Information to Mayor's office, June - Mayor's Proposal, Market 5 Gallery; July-- Bridges, A Ward 6 Newsletter; Oct -- Establishment of Eastern Market Planning Committee, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Community Development Corporation: April -- Eastern Market Planning Committee Subcommittee on Tenant Mix and Architectural Design, re: Central Market Design Alternate; July -- re: Cooper Lecky, Architects Proposal, Eastern Market Survey, Eastern Market Miscellany, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Community Development Corporation: May -- Work Proposal from The Franz Group, Inc., to office of the Mayor, 1986 June (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Community Development Corporation: June --November Reports to the Mayor, meetings, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Community Development Corporation: Dec - Articles of Incorporation, correspondence, task force, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Community Development Corporation: January -- Articles of Incorporation, budget, Bylaws, correspondence, other markets, taskforce, testimony, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Community Development Corporation: February -- Articles of Incorporation, correspondence, taskforce, DC Register Part 2 -- D.C. Procurement Regulations, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Community Development Corporation: March-- Board of Directors, Newsletter, Articles of Incorporation, Contract, Executive Committee, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Community Development Corporation: April -- Board of Directors, Bylaws, Correspondence, other market, Cooper-Lecky Architects, D.C. Government Bureau of Material Management Negotiated Services Contract, Public Relations, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Community Development Corporation: April, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Community Development Corporation: May - Streetscape, Traffic and Parking, Newsletter, Board of Directors, Cooper-Lecky Architects, Executive Committee, correspondence with D.C. government, Memorandum of Understanding Sample, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Community Development Corporation: June -- Board of Directors, Eastern Market Renovation Project, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Community Development Corporation: July -- Streetscape, Traffic, and Parking, Board of Directors, Committees, position descriptions, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Community Development Corporation: August-- grocery store issue, Executive Committee, Board of Directors, New York Times article about Eastern Market, Cooper Lecky, Architects, Eastern Market Renovation Phase II, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Community Development Corporation: September -- Capitol Hill Restoration Society, Board of Directors, Administrative Assistant Position Description, newsletter, Treasurer's Report, Hill Rag, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Community Development Corporation: October-- Capitol Hill Restoration Society, Board of Directors, correspondence with D.C. Council, Executive and Marketing Management Committees, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Community Development Corporation: November -- Executive Committee, Architectural/ Renovation Management Committee, budget, Streetscape, Traffic and Parking Committee, Liability Insurance for Nonprofits article, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Community Development Corporation: December-- Parking, Executive Committee, Board of Directors, Capitol Hill Group Ministry, Renovation, note re: Market Master position, correspondence, Memorandum of Agreement, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Community Development Corporation: January -- Board of Directors, Exec Co, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Community Development Corporation: February -- Business Plan, Board of Directors, PEPCO, Cooper-Lecky Architects, Executive Committee, Karen Walker correspondence, Treasurer's Report, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Community Development Corporation: March -- Streetscape, Board of Directors, project delay, Karen Walker statement to Committee of Housing and Economic Development of the Council of the District of Columbia, Business Plan, Executive Committee, Management Concept, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Community Development Corporation: April -- Market 5 Gallery, Master Agreement, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 11)